<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="weston_rotator">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2020 Collabora Ltd.

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT.  IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="Protocol for dynamic orientation of an output">
    Weston extension that specifies an interface which clients can use to pass
    a new transform value to the compositor. Client are responsible for sending the
    transform value as this allows the ability to use an external sensor, like
    an accelerometer in order to read out the data independently in a different
    process (APIs might be lacking an event-based reading mechanism).
    Also, interactively changing the orientation might be
    something desirable to have and this satisfies that requirement as well.
  </description>

  <interface name="weston_rotator" version="1">
    <description summary="weston rotator">
    The interface is advertised as a global object through wl_registry.
    </description>

    <request name="rotate">
      <description summary="perform a rotation">
        This request is used to tell the compositor the new transform value.
        A client can use the 'accelerometer' field, under the form of a string,
        if it intends to use a sensor (like an 'accelerometer'), or can use a
        wl_output object instead if it knows which output to apply the
        transform to.

        For the latter, clients can use human-readable description from the
        xdg_output interface, together with the wl_output interface to identify
        which wl_output belongs to that human-readable output name.

        For the former, additional configuration is required to match the output
        on which this 'accelerometer' should apply the new transform. The
        compositor can identify which output to apply the transform by matching
        the 'accelerometer' assigned to.  A special dedicated section, called
        '[accelerometer]' has been added which allows to identify the 'accelerometer'
        by name.

        The request will be dismissed if both an 'accelerometer' and 'output'
        fields are set, and only one of them are permitted. A 'done' event will be
        sent to the client with an invalid transform value.
      </description>
      <arg name="accelerometer" type="string" allow-null="true"/>
      <arg name="output" type="object" interface="wl_output" allow-null="true"/>
      <arg name="transform" type="uint" enum="wl_output_transform" />
    </request>

    <event name="done">
      <description summary="signals when the rotation has been applied">
        Event sent when the orientation of the output has been applied.
        Client can use the transform value received here to check against the
        one passed in 'rotate' request to verify it was applied. This event can
        also be used in case client doesn't install a handler wl_output.geometry()
        event (as that event will distribute the new transform value).
      </description>
      <arg name="transform" type="uint" enum="wl_output_transform" />
    </event>

  </interface>
</protocol>
